Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs, XIII.
  - Non World War II, 1.
    - Spanish American War
      - Published Images, 1898 - 1915 (Box Photo 3, Folder 9-16)
        - American sailors close aboard Maine after hanging a wreath from the wrecked battleship's mainmast, 25.
        - Numerous wreaths adorn Maine's mainmast from which also files the Stars and Strips at half-mast., 26.
          Photo number: 1-28
        - Maine's wreck the morning after the explosion, 27.
          Photo number: 1-29
        - Funeral procession for Maine's dead, 28.
          Photo number: 1-30
        - A contemporary cartoon reflects typical reactions to Maine's sinking., 29.
          Photo number: 1-31
        - The Maine court of inquiry examines Ens. Wilfred V. N. Powelson (third from right) on board the lighthouse tender Mangrove in Havana harbor., 30.
          Members of the court include (left to right) Capts. French E. Chadwick and William T. Sampson and Lt. Cmdrs. William R. Potter and Adolph Marix. Powelson, assigned to the transport Fern, headed the diving operations on Maine's wreck. The court examined him on at least five occasions.
          Photo number: 1-32
        - "Cuba libre!", 31.
          Photo number: 1-33
        - The San Carlos Club in Santiago – hotbed of sentiment for the annexation of Cuba to the United States, 32.
          Photo number: 1-34
        - Artist's rendition of President McKinley signing the American signing the American ultimatum to the Spanish government, 33.
          Photo number: 1-35
        - A dapper prospective recruit studies enlistment circulars in front of a post office branch in New York City under the watchful eyes of a private and corporal., 34.
        - Other prospects ask another corporal about enlistment., 35.
        - While spending "a few moments" in the squad room above the post office, recruits learn their first hard lesson about life in the Army – "Hurry up and wait.", 36.
        - While filling out enlistment papers, recruits undergo close questioning by the recruiting sergeant., 37.
        - As the recruiting sergeant looks on, an officer administers the oath of enlistment to the new enlistee., 38.
        - "You're in the Army!", 39.
          Newly enlisted men draw uniforms at the recruiting station.
        - View of the training camp at Montauk, New York, on the eastern tip of Long Island, 40.
        - Field officers of the 1st Volunteer Cavalry, or "Rough Riders," relax in front of their tent while their unit trains at the International Fairgrounds in San Antonio, Texas, during May 1898., 41.
          They are (left to right) Lt. Col. Theodore Roosevelt, Col. Leonard Wood, and Maj. Alexander Brodie.
        - Officer's mess in the Rough Riders' camp in San Antonio, with Colonel Wood and Roosevelt seated at the head of the table., 42.
        - A New York volunteer infantry regiment drills in camp at Greenville, South Carolina., 43.
        - Prisoners grade an area near the hospital at Camp McKenzie, Georgia., 44.
        - African-American soldiers of the 3rd Alabama National Guard pose at Camp Shipp, near Anniston, in east central Alabama., 45.
        - Men line up for dinner at Camp Alger near Fairfax, Virginia., 46.
        - Men at Camp Alger gather round a photographer while he works his "Biograph," preparing for a unit portrait., 47.
        - Payday at Camp Alger fro the 8th Ohio Volunteers, on the day they left for Tampa, Florida, in 1898, 48.
        - After loading a wagon, the 8th Ohio breaks camp., 49.
        - The 8th Ohio marches away from Camp Alger for the last time, taking the step from regimental field music, probably the traditional tune, "The Girl I Left Behind Me.", 50.
        - An artillery unit's limbers lie ready for transport to Tampa, lashed and secured to the bed of a Seaboard Air Line flatcar., 51.
        - The men of the 4th Artillery draw an admiring crowd as they depart fro Tampa and points south., 52.
        - The 21st U.S. Regulars board a passenger train in Plattsburg, New York., 53.
        - In a scene that must have quickened pulses and moistened many an eye, the 9th Massachusetts Volunteers depart Clinton, Massachusetts, on May 4, 1898., 54.
        - Freight cars carrying equipment for the expedition to Cuba crowd into the railyard in Tampa., 55.
        - The 9th U.S. Infantry, one of the most photographed units of the Santiago Campaign, encamped in a dry, sandy, piney wood in the marshaling area near Tampa., 56.
        - One of the more fortunate officers accompanied by his wife, 57.
        - "To the rear in open order, march! Inspection arms.", 58.
          Troops of the 9thh Infantry stand at attention for firearms inspection by a junior officer. Photographs 2-25, 2-26, and 2-27 were taken by Capt. Willis Wittich, a prolific photographer in Florida and in Cuba.
        - Prone firing exercises in the camps at Tampa, 59.
          Photo number: 2-26
        - The 21st Infantry on a dusty practice march, 60.
          Photo number: 2-27
        - Weighing an issue of beef for the men of the 21st infantry, 61.
          Photo number: 2-28
        - Parched and sweat-drenched in the near-tropical Florida climate, men line up at the sound of mess call, awaiting their repast among the pines., 62.
          Photo number: 2-29
        - Regulars of Company A, 2d Infantry mug for the camera while savoring their evening meal in Tampa., 63.
          Photo number: 2-30
        - William McKinley, Jr. president of the United States, 64.
        - William Randolph Hearst, publisher of the New York Journal, 65.
        - Stewart L. Woodford, U.S. minister to Spain, 66.
        - William R. Day, U.S. secretary of state, 67.
        - Russell A. Alger, U.S. secretary of war, 68.
        - John D. Long, U.S. secretary of the navy, 69.
        - Maj. Gen. William R. Shafter, commanding general, V Corps, 70.
        - Calixto García Íñiguez, commanding general, Cuban troops, province of Santiago, 71.
        - Commodore George Dewey, commander, U.S. naval forces, Asiatic Station, 72.
        - Alfonso XIII, king of Spain, 73.
        - Don Carlos, pretender to the Spanish throne, 74.
        - General Valeriano Weyler y Nicolau, governor general of Cuba before the outbreak of hostilities, 75.
        - Práxedes Sagasta, Spanish prime minister, 76.
        - Capt. Gen. Ramón Blanco y Erenas, governor general of Cuba, 77.
        - Brig. Gen. Arsenio Linares y Pomba, commanding general army corps, Santiago, 78.
        - Admiral Pascual Cervera y Topete, commander, Spanish naval squadron before Santiago, 79.
        - Admiral Manuel de la Cámara y Libermoore, commander, Spanish naval squadron in Spanish waters, 80.
        - Admiral Patricio Montojo y Parasón, commander, Spanish naval squadron off Manila Bay, 81.
        - U.S. regulars from the 12th Infantry stand ready fro action, armed with Krag-Jörgensen rifles., 82.
        - American infantry dug in on a firing line during exercises in camp near Tampa., 83.
        - Krag-Jörgensen Model 1892 .30-caliber rifle and cavalry carbine, both generally issued to regulars., 84.
          Note the snap-on, tinned hood covering the carbine's front sight, in place to protect the sight in the saddle scabbard.
        - Springfield rifles, Model 1873, .45-.70 caliber, issued to volunteer units due to a shortage of Krag-Jörgensen, 85.
        - A horse-drawn artillery piece with limber in one of the many camps surrounding Tampa during the summer of 1898, 86.
        - A Gatling gun parked in the tall grass behind the siege lines at Santiago, 87.
        - The famous Sims-Dudley dynamite gun in Tampa on its way to a Cuba-bound transport, probably Leona, to which the 10th Cavalry was assigned, 88.
        - Army pack mules during the Santiago Campaign, 89.
        - A mule-drawn U.S. Army ambulance before being loaded at Tampa., 90.
        - The main road leading to Güines, Cuba, 91.
        - The "road" between La Sierra and San Blas, Cuba, 92.
        - The battleship Oregon off San Francisco, March 19, 1898, 93.
        - Sailors practice loading one of the 8-inch/.35-caliber BLRs of the armored cruiser New York, circa 1898., 94.
        - After her maiden voyage from England, the armored cruiser Amazonas (soon to be renamed New Orleans) arrives at the New York Navy Yard on April 15, 1898., 95.
        - The auxiliary cruiser Yankee fits out at the New York Navy Yard on April 27, 1898., 96.
        - The Civil War-era monitor, Jason, originally named Sangamon and a veteran of service in the North Atlantic and South Atlantic blockade squadrons, fits out at the New York Navy Yard on May 28, 1898., 97.
        - Proud and defiant, a Cuban soldier is ready for action against the Spanish., 98.
        - Cubans irregulars meet Americans during the advance from Siboney in June 1898., 99.
        - Members of the 25th Company, Alfonso Guards, stand proudly in front of their barracks in Puerto Rico., 100.
        - The Spanish Mauser, Model 1893, issued to Spanish troops serving in Cuba, 101.
          Page number: 41
        - The Mercedes Barracks situated on a broad plateau outside the city of Santiago, 102.
        - Redoubt Chipre outside the city of Havana, Cuba., 103.
          Note the sandbagged construction.
        - Redoubt Mordazo, a Spanish log-and-sand earthwork in the network of defenses surrounding Havana, 104.
        - Barbed-wire entanglements in front of Redoubt Mazo near Havana, 105.
        - Armored railway cars at Sagua la Grande, Cuba, 106.
        - A 12-inch gun at the Santa Clara battery near Vedado, 107.
        - Large-bore muzzle-loading Parrott rifles on the Santiago defenses, 108.
        - Smoothbore, 5-inch Spanish artillery piece from the early nineteenth century in the defensive lines before Santiago, 109.
        - Hotchkiss guns guard the entrance to Santiago harbor. Morro Castle lies in the background., 110.
        - Spanish fort at the harbor near Cienfuegos, Cuba, 111.
        - Draw-bridge and entrance to the keep of El Castillo at Cienfuegos, 112.
        - Spanish blockhouse under construction near Santiago, 113.
        - Complete blockhouse at Caibarién, Cuba, 114.
        - Loopholed house at La Sierra, 115.
        - Spanish blockhouse converted from a church near Rincón, 116.
        - Blockhouse commanding the north end of a railroad embankment near Isabella de Saqua, 117.
        - Admiral Cervera's squadron at Saint Vincent, Cape Verde Islands, Between April 19 and 29, 1898, 118.
        - A sailor on board the Spanish armored cruiser Vizcaya demonstrates the workings of 5.5-inch gun, the standard secondary battery weapon on board that vessel and her two ill-fated sister ships, Almirante Oquendo and Infanta Maria Teresa., 119.
        - The battleship Oregon during its voyage around South America to Cuba, 120.
        - The protected cruiser Olympia at Hong Kong, circa April 1898., 121.
          Note that lead gray color has replaced the peacetime white-and-straw scheme Commodore George Dewey's flag flies on the main.
        - Capt. Charles V. Gridley, Olympia's commanding officer, 122.
        - Postwar view of the protected cruiser Baltimore, in peacetime white-and-straw color scheme, with laundry festooning the forward rigging, 123.
        - Capt. Nehemiah M Dyer, Baltimore's commanding officer, 124.
        - The protected cruiser Raleigh, 125.
        - Capt. Joseph B. Goghlan, Raleigh's commanding officer, 126.
        - The gunboat Petrel at Hong Kong April 15, 1898, 127.
        - Cmdr. Edward P. Wood, Petrel's commanding officer, 128.
        - The gunboat Concord, 129.
        - Cmdr. Asa Walker, Concord's commanding officer, 130.
        - The protected cruiser Boston, 131.
        - Capt. Frank Wildes, Boston's commanding officer, 132.
        - The revenue cutter McCulloch served as a valuable auxiliary to Dewey's squadron, 133.
        - Capt. Daniel B. Hodgsdon, Revenue Cutter Service, McCulloch's commanding officer, 134.
        - The supply ship Zafiro, 135.
        - The collier Nanshan, December 26, 1915, 136.
        - Alfonso Saenz's depiction of the Battle Manila Bay, showing the protected cruiser Olympia leading the American line of battle., 137.
          The protected cruisers Baltimore and Raleigh and gunboats Petrel and Concord follow; the protected cruiser Boston brings up the rear.
        - Commodore Dewey, wearing a rakish, nonregulation touring cap, confers with Capt. Charles V. Gridley, Olympia's commanding officer, and his chief of staff Cmdr. Benjamin P. Lamberton, during the 7:35 A.M. to 11:16 A.M. lull in the action at Manila Bay., 138.
        - In this artist's depiction, sailors on board Olympia, some stripped to the waist, take a breather during the lull in the action on May 1., 139.
        - The Spanish unprotected cruiser Reina Cristina, flagship of the Spanish squadron. Later off Cavite, 140.
        - The sunken Spanish unprotected cruiser Castilla., 141.
          The U.S. protected cruisers Olympia and Baltimore can be seen in background (left).
        - The iron-hulled unprotected cruiser Don Antonio de Ulloa, sunk off Cavite, 142.
        - The gunboats Isla de Luzon (left) and Isla de Cuba; the latter was the ship to which Admiral Montojo shifted his flag after American gunfire disabled his flagship Reina Cristina., 143.
        - Looking aft on board Isla de Luzon. Isla de Cuba lies in background., 144.
        - Looking forward from Isla de Cuba's poop deck., 145.
        - Lt. Cmdr. Edward M. Hughes, executive officer of the gunboat Petrel, who led a seven-man party from the ship to burn Spanish men-of-war off Cavite., 146.
        - Party of sailors from the gunboat Petrel boarding and setting Spanish gunboat afire off Cavite, May 1, 1898., 147.
        - Panorama of destruction off Cavite., 148.
          The transport Isla de Mindanao (left), gunboats Isla de Luzon and Velasco (right); U.S. gunboat Petrel is in the distant background. Note Isla de Luzon's blackened stern, and one of her four 4.7-inch Hontoria rifles.
        - A sailor on board Olympia poses by the dented plate on the starboard side of the superstructure, just forward of the second 5-inch gun sponson., 149.
          This was the only scar the cruiser received (faintly visible to the right of the rope).
        - One of Olympia's mascots, this parrot, is said to have lost a leg at Manila Bay., 150.
        - Lt. Dion Williams, USMC, and a portion of the Marine guard from the protected cruiser Baltimore, which occupied the Cavite navy yard on May 3, 1898, 151.
        - First reinforcement for Dewey's squadron came in the form of the protected cruiser Charleston., 152.
        - The transport City of Pekin, one of the three troops transport convoyed by Charleston, en route to Manila, 153.
        - The monitor Manadnock, as seen from the collier Nero, en route to the Philippines, demonstrates the seagoing qualities for which monitors were justly infamous – her main deck awash., 154.
        - The battleship Pelayo moored at Port Said, Egypt, between June 22 and July 11, 1898, 155.
        - The armored cruiser Carlos V at Port Said, on either June 22 or July 1, 1898., 156.
          Vessel in left back-ground is either the Colón or Covadonga, merchant steamships requisitioned to navel service. At right is the stern of the naval steamship Buenos Aires.
        - The armed merchant cruiser Patriota, Port Said, on either June 22 or July 11, 1898., 157.
          She had been acquired as the steamship Normannia from the Lloyd Line.
        - The gunboat Nashville (right) inaugurates the blockade, stopping the Spanish merchantman Buena Ventura, April 22, 1898, 158.
        - Rufus F. Zogbaum's sketch of the first Spanish prisoners of war, captured on board the Spanish steamer Argonauta on April 26, 1898, 159.
        - Artist Henry Reuterdahl's impression of the bombardment of Matanzas on April 27, 1838, 160.
        - Lithograph depicting the cutting of one of the telegraph cables linking Cienfuegos and Havana, May 11, 1898., 161.
        - Launch from the gunboat Nashville, used in severing the cable at Cienfuegos., 162.
        - Seaman Willard D. Miller of the gunboat Nashville, a Canadian, earned the Medal of Honor for cutting the Spanish telegraph cable off Cienfuegos., 163.
        - Seaman Harry H. Miller served alongside his brother Willard in Nashville and also received the Medal of Honor for heroism off Cienfuegos., 164.
        - Lt. John B. Bernadou commanding officer of the torpedo boat Winslow, wounded in action at Cárdenas., 165.
        - Artist's depiction of the revenue cutter Hudson towing the disabled torpedo boat Winslow out of range of Spanish guns off Cárdenas, Cuba, May 11, 1898., 166.
        - Winslow's after conning tower, showing indentations from Spanish shell hits, 167.
        - Ens. Worth Bagley, photographed at Key West, Florida, circa March 1898, 168.
        - The collier Merrimac fitting out for service, Norfolk Navy Yard, April 23, 1898, 169.
        - Assistant Naval Constructor Richmond P. Hobson, 170.
        - Artist conception of Merrimac being sunk off Estrella PArtist conception of Merrimac being sunk off Estrella Point, near the channel to Santiago harbor, by heavy Spanish gunfireoint, near the channel to Santiago harbor, by heavy Spanish gunfire, 171.
        - Views from El Morro shows the sunken Reina Mercedes in the foreground and the tip of Merrimac's masts and stack., 172.
        - Close-up of the wreck of the collier Merrimac, sunk near the channel at Santiago., 173.
        - Spanish prisoners – 1st Lt. Pius Giner Gastaminza, of the 6th Battalion, Lower Peninsula Infantry among them – on their way to be exchanged for Hobson and his Merrimac crew, near Santiago., 174.
        - Hobson leads his men back to American lines., 175.
          The Spanish released them in exchange for captured Spanish soldiers.
        - As Hobson's men pass, one soldier respectfully doff his campaign hat while another rushes up to rear of the wagon that is carrying (front to rear Gunner's Mate First Class George Charrette, Machinist First Class George F. Philips, and Walter Tender Francis Kelly., 176.
        - As word of the arrival of Hobson's crew spreads, American soldiers throng around them to welcome them back., 177.
        - Cmdr. Bowman H. McCalla, captain of the unprotected cruiser Marblehead, who supervised the landings at Guantánamo Bay in June 1989., 178.
        - The cruiser Marblehead as she appeared during the war with Spain., 179.
        - The transport Panther (seen) here as the passenger steamship Venezuela under way in New York Harbor) transported Marines to Guantánamo Bay., 180.
        - Lt. Col. Robert W. Huntington who had fought at Bull Run, commanded the 1st Marine Battalion., 181.
        - Camp McCalla, named in honor of Marblehead's captain, atop the hill (background, left) overlooking the beach, 182.
        - Graves of "the First Martyrs," Pvts. James McGolgan and James Dumphy and Acting Assistant Surgeon John B. Gibbs, among the tents of Camp McCalla, late June 1898., 183.
          Spanish pressure on the entrenchments had compelled the Marines to bury their dead inside the camp itself.
        - Artist's conception of Marines at Guantánamo, aided by the cruiser Marblehead's searchlights, repelling the first Spanish attack on the night of June 11-12, 1898, 184.
        - Artist F.C. Yohn's depiction of Marines returning Spanish fire at Guantánamo being reinforced by their shipmates from camp., 185.
          While Yohn's depiction of the Marines' headgear (undress caps) is correct, he inaccurately shows them in blues – they landed clad in brown linen campaign uniforms.
        - Assistant Surgeon John B. Gibbs, the only naval medical officer to die in the Spanish-American War, 186.
        - While a fatigued leatherneck takes a breather seated in the lip of a wheelbarrow, two Cuban soldiers, attired in U.S. Navy white duck uniforms, stand nearby., 187.
        - 1st Lt. Henry L. Draper USMC, adjunct of the First Marine Battalion, raises the Stars and Stripes over Camp McCalla., 188.
        - The dispatch boat Dolphin, as she appeared in the 1890s, 189.
        - Diorama depicting the heroism of Sgt. John H. Quick, "with the utmost coolness" signaling the dispatch boat Dolphin, which is mistakenly shelling 2d Lt. Louis J. Magill's platoon during the Cuzco Well fight, June 14, 1898., 190.
          Quick was awarded the Medal of Honor.
        - This leather neck, his Lee-Metford rifle across his lap, rests in the shade of a rude lean-to at Camp McCalla, June 17, 1898., 191.
          More practical campaign hats arrived four days later.
        - Overall view of Guantánamo Bay, June 26, 1898, showing the Cuban camp (lower left); ships sheltering in the harbor include the gunboat Bancroft, cruiser Detroit and Marblehead, and battleship Oregon., 192.
        - Tents come down at Tampa as the 9th Infantry breaks camp and make ready for embarkation to Cuba., 193.
        - While one of their company officers looks on, men of the 21st Infantry load their equipment into boxcars., 194.
        - A trooper from Troop D, 2d Cavalry, coxes a horse into a Seaboard Air Line livestock car bound for the SS Morgan., 195.
        - The finger piers and jetties of Port Tampa, 196.
        - Railway cars carrying men and equipment of the Cuban expedition transform the docks at Port Tampa into a logistical nightmare., 197.
        - Infantry men trudge across the tracks toward what they hope will be their assigned transport., 198.
        - The colors of the 1st Infantry move toward the long-anticipated embarkation onto the transports., 199.
        - Lt. Col. William Bisbee (left), sword resting on his right shoulder, leads his 1st Infantry onto the gangplank of the transport Segurança, which is just out of view at left., 200.
        - The 9th Infantry boards the Santiago., 201.
          The Krag rifle of the first sergeant at left is protected by a canvas covering.
        - The long wait proved to be too much for these regulars., 202.
        - The Rough Riders from the 1st Volunteer Cavalry, without their horses, clamber on board the Yucatan for the sea journey to Cuba., 203.
        - Horses and mules await their turn to board the ships moored to the docks at Port Tampa., 204.
        - With the assistance of a ship's cargo crane, men load Cuba-bound light artillery pieced onto a transport (either the Berkshire or Coma)., 205.
        - Ammunition and supplies being loaded into a vessel's cargo hold at Port Tampa, 206.
        - The units that made up the Santiago expedition:, 207.
        - Ready to commence their voyage into the Caribbean, loaded transports move out into Tampa Bay., 208.
          The Comal's stern is visible at center.
        - The transport Seneca (designated Army Transport No. 5) moves into Tampa Bay., 209.
          Note the men climbing onto her masts.
        - The Knickerbocker (left) and City of Washington (right) lie alongside each other before the voyage to Cuba., 210.
        - Under way at last!, 211.
          One of the lead vessels in the Santiago expedition steams ahead, leaving a large number of vessels in her wake.
        - The transport Matteawan, her "designating number" 26 on her funnel, steams toward Cuba., 212.
        - Troops crowd the upper decks of the transport City of Washington, en route to Cuba., 213.
        - The Saratoga steams into the Gulf during the voyage to Cuba., 214.
        - Having grabbed the first available berths, these lucky soldiers have a proper place to sleep., 215.
        - Foreign military attachés on board a Cuba-bound transport, likely the Segurança, 216.